<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://shawn.cheesesnakes.net/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://shawn.cheesesnakes.net/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-10-19T12:08:24+00:00</updated><id>https://shawn.cheesesnakes.net/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Shawn Dsouza</title><subtitle>A place to find my academic work and writing. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Locked down in a port town.</title><link href="https://shawn.cheesesnakes.net/blog/2020/Lockdown/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Locked down in a port town."/><published>2020-08-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-08-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://shawn.cheesesnakes.net/blog/2020/Lockdown</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://shawn.cheesesnakes.net/blog/2020/Lockdown/"><![CDATA[<p><img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/rampan_pulling.png"/></p> <p>In early March 2020, I travelled to Malvan where, for the past 3 years, I’ve been studying the fisheries in the region. Malvan is a small coastal town in Sindhudurg, the southernmost district of Maharashtra. I had planned to map the fisheries using a collaborative approach with the fishers. I was hoping for interviews and a return to field work after almost a year working in the lab and the office back in Bangalore. It was a much-needed change of pace. However, like the fishers and traders of Malvan, the researchers also did not have a clue of what was to come in the following days and months.</p> <p>Little seemed to have changed in Malvan. The boats still plied every day, the markets were full of people and the fish auctions still raged on, the crowds a little thinner than I remembered. The tourists were flooding in for the start of the summer and business was good for the local shacks, restaurants and water sports. I was able to get some field work done in the first couple of weeks in March. All the while we were a bit cut off from the news, so when the lockdown did happen as seemed inevitable later, it was a bit of a surprise to all of us at that point.</p> <p>By mid–march, news of the looming pandemic had become part of everyday conversation. I remember a trawler captain coming up to me at the auction, after 3 days out at sea, and asking me “He coronavirus kay ahe? Amhala kahi hou shakta ka?” (What’s this coronavirus? Will it affect us here in Malvan?) An elderly gentleman, who used to be an auctioneer but is now retired, came up to me and said “Look at this!” handing me his smart phone. On it was a video of how a virus or contagion spreads from one person to another. “This is how it will get us”, he remarked.</p> <p>The announcements from the local bureaucracy had already started. A small tempo - rickshaw would come around with a loud speaker that blared best practices for keeping yourself protected from the virus – ‘Wash your hands! Don’t touch your face! Avoid crowded places!’. We could hear these announcements in the background as we went about our usual business, completely ignorant of how they would soon be at the forefront of our everyday life. Our friends in the cities started posting stuff about universities closing down, curfews at night and increased police presence, while around us the tourists trickled to a halt and restaurants and tourism businesses shut shop. Suddenly Malvan was much quieter through the day.</p> <p>Then came the Janata curfew, which was a quiet affair here, at least on Dandi beach. The houses were too far apart to hear the banging of pots and pan, if there was any. Soon after, the Tahsildar and the superintendent of police at Malvan came and met with the auctioneers and fishers present at the evening auction. They announced that the auction was now not feasible given the progression of the pandemic. And as abruptly as that, the auctions stopped. It was difficult to imagine Malvan without the daily auction. But there it was.</p> <p>The last of the tourists left just before the announcement of the lockdown. The beaches of Malvan, once bustling with activity through the day and even into the night, fell silent. The sounds of boat motors and rickshaws transporting fish could no longer be heard in the mornings. Around 70 medium sized fishing trawlers with crews of 8 – 9 each lay dormant, docked in the natural harbour at Dandi beach. Even the drone of jet skis and the tourists yelling while riding them during the day disappeared.</p> <p>Reports of tons of fish being thrown overboard due to a lack of demand started flooding in from major ports like Mumbai and Porbandar. Instagram, Facebook and Twitter were flooded with the plight of migrant workers stranded in different parts of the country. In Malvan though, our concerns were more mundane. Supplies started to run low and it was unclear where one could get simple things like rice or medicines. The narrow streets of the town centre were now blocked by police check posts. The atmosphere at the time was one of fear and uncertainty.</p> <p>The weeks passed and the first lockdown was almost at an end. “We won’t be affected” said a fish trader who I ran into on the beach, with the owner of my favourite chai tapri alongside him. The two were out for a stroll because there wasn’t anything better to do. People would roam the beaches every evening; some would just sit at the periphery of their houses waving at people passing by. On some evenings, a group of local traders and fishers would get together for a match of cricket. The mother of a fisher who was playing cricket said ”The police come every evening at 6 and chase us away, we’ll get fined Rs. 1000 for not wearing a mask”.</p> <p>The start of the lockdown saw a total curb on all fishing activity. During the second phase of the lockdown, however, restrictions on fishing were lifted, fishers were now allowed to go out but had to market the catch themselves. The beach was vibrant with the bustling of small gillnet boats almost immediately. Fish flooded the market but there was no one to buy. The price of fish had dropped significantly during this time. One could see an army of fisherwomen sitting neatly at a distance of 6 feet from each other at market all the while watched over by an army of police, lest one got too close to the other.</p> <p>Towards the end of the second lockdown people started getting a bit bolder about leaving their houses. Sindhudurg was declared a green zone with only 1 case being reported since the disease had been declared a pandemic. Shops began to open, yet nothing seemed to approach normal. A gillnet fisher told me that most of them were going out to sea twice a day, ‘What else is there to do?’ he remarked. The price of fish had fallen to around Rs 50 per basket. ‘A man needs at least Rs. 300 per day to get by’, he said.</p> <p>The ice factory behind our field base bustled with activity. At times, a long line of trucks waiting for ice would form. The trawlers had started to ply regularly again. Even the daily fish sale auctions had started in places along the coast like Devgad and Vengurla, and Malvan was soon to follow. An area on the beach designated by the authorities was flattened and lined with ropes in preparation for the auction. Auction agents lined up six feet apart, every one wearing a mask. Malvan, like the rest of India and the world, would slowly inch towards its new normal. Could the scenes of crowded markets with people gathered around large baskets of fish now be a thing of the past? Aggregators and home delivery seem to now be thriving in hubs like Mumbai and Bangalore. The same may soon be the fate of Malvan.</p> <p>My teammates and I were able to make our way to back home to Mumbai around mid–April. In early June, Cyclone Nisarga caused yet another disruption to what has been a season filled with misfortune for fishers on the west coast of India. Even as things slowly open up in ‘Unlock 1’ or ‘Mission Begin Again’, India’s fishers may find it increasingly difficult to adjust to their new normal.</p>]]></content><author><name>Shawn Dsouza</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[An article about my experience being on field during the COVID - 19 lockdown. Pulished in The Bastion.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Sailing into an uncertain sea</title><link href="https://shawn.cheesesnakes.net/blog/2019/Sailing/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sailing into an uncertain sea"/><published>2019-08-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-08-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://shawn.cheesesnakes.net/blog/2019/Sailing</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://shawn.cheesesnakes.net/blog/2019/Sailing/"><![CDATA[<p>This is a story about trawl-fishing, about the lives of the people who depend on this dying industry and the reasons for its inevitable demise. Ultimately, it seems likely that the industry is destined for collapse, doomed by its own brutal efficiency. But what does this mean for individual fishers? How are we preparing for a time when trawl-fishing is no longer able to provide jobs to the millions that have depended upon it for decades and what is the future of those people?</p> <p><em>Left anchorage at 6 a.m., the crew still brushing their teeth. A full moon casts a yellow light over calm waters. The sun will not rise for another hour. The Indian fishing town of Malvan recedes into the darkness.</em></p> <p>Around the globe, mechanised trawler-boats have become one of the mainstays of commercial fishing. Although they vary massively in scale, the principle is the same – a net is cast from the back of a motorised vessel and towed for a number of hours. Sometimes the net is dragged along the sea-floor, sometimes it hangs midway in the water column. In either case, whatever marine life is in the net’s path, it is caught up and mechanical winches then haul it aboard the boat.</p> <p><em>Once in deeper waters, winches begin whirring, ropes begin to play out and the net is cast for the first time of the day…</em></p> <p>Trawling is a hugely effective way of extracting marine resources with a high market value. However, the problem lies in its indiscriminate nature. A whole suite of organisms that are not targeted or commercially valuable end up in trawl nets. These range from juvenile fish to sea turtles to sea snakes (Soykan et al. 2008).</p> <p>These two factors—the large number of boats operating throughout the tropics and the broad range of species which are caught—have set in motion a chain of events which are having severe consequences, both for marine ecosystems and fisher communities (Eayrs 2007).</p> <p>First, due to the effectiveness of the technique, trawling has been one of the factors which has caused dramatic declines in stocks of highly prized commercial species such as anchoveta (Engraulis ringens) in Peru and other South American countries, and prawn stocks in Southeast Asia and Australia (Gillett 2008; FAO 2018). Some fisheries experts say that because stocks of target species are in such a depleted state, there are now none which can be ‘sustainably’ harvested. There are just those for which harvesting is slightly less unsustainable than others.</p> <p>The next link in the chain is the commercialisation of by-catch. By-catch is all the sea-life which was not being targeted, but which was caught incidentally due to the non-selectivity of the trawl nets. By-catch is estimated to account for around 40% of the global marine catch and has traditionally had little market value (Kelleher 2005). In the past, therefore, much of it was thrown back into the sea. Now however, as stocks of target species decline, fishers are forced to commercialise more of this by-catch to maintain income-levels (Lobo et al. 2010; Nunoo et al. 2009).</p> <p><em>…and in the two hours in which the net will be pulled through the water, there is time to speak with the crew. Deepak is young – he can be no more than 22. His arms are strong and on one is a heart tattoo, with the initials of a past girlfriend. When asked about it, he smiles bashfully. Anil meanwhile has been working on fishing boats since he was 14 or 15. Now 46, he is one of the most experienced members of the crew. Direct and straightforward, Anil answers questions in the same way that that he and his crew-mates complete all tasks aboard the boat. Here in Malvan he earns about Rs100 a day (less than 1 ½ USD). With this money he supports his family at home in Karwar, Karnataka: his wife, son and two daughters, the eldest of whom is in her secondyear at university. The crew take shore-leave on rotation and having just returned, Anil will now not see his family for four to five months. By working on a trawler, Anil is able to provide his family with comparative financial security. It is true that were he to get injured, there is no health insurance on these boats and the owner would provide no financial assistance with medical costs. He previously worked as a small-scale gill-net vessel, a way of life which neither required such long spells at sea, nor so much time away from his family, but which compelled a more-or-less hand-to-mouth existence. Now on the trawler he has a reliable income and earns enough to make life more comfortable for his family. He does not have a passion for the ocean, or for this way of life – it is simply a job. But it is one that he and his family depend on for their health and livelihood.</em></p> <p><em>At 8.30 a.m. the net is winched in. By 8.50 a.m. the catch has been landed onto the boat and an hour and a half later it has been sorted, the target and trash-fish boxed, the discards thrown overboard. Sorting is done by hand with dust-pans and plastic scrapers. Venomous sea snakes are buried amidst the squirming, salty pile. Bites are not uncommon.</em></p> <p><em>10.30 a.m. – breakfast. Fish curry and rice, cooked below deck at the prow, by the ship-cook Shivram.</em></p> <p><em>The net was re-cast for a second trawl almost as soon as the first was hauled up – there will be four today. Despite the aid of mechanised winches, the physical exertion required by the crew is immense. As is the potential danger. Men run along the gunwales as the small boat pitches, wheels spin, cranks pull and taut metal lines thrum and strain. Although regularly maintained, the machinery is decades old and flecked with rust. Not one of the fishers is without scars.</em></p> <p>As a testament to the ingenuity of the fishing economy, a number of markets have been established for by-catch which previously had no commercial value. Some is sold for food, with re-branding or euphemistic names used to entice customers, such as crab cake, or the better-known fish oils and other dietary supplements. Most, however is dried, ground down into powder and made into fishmeal. This is then used in animal feeds (ironically this includes food for fish farms, which have been proposed as one solution to overfishing) and fertilisers (Edwards and Allan 2004).</p> <p><em>12.30 p.m. – lunch. Fried fish and rice. After the meal everyone does their own washing up, including the Captain, Yeshwant. He chews a mouthful of saunf (fennel seeds) and the cabin is filled with the sweet smell.</em></p> <p>But as with stocks of commercial species, it seems inevitable that the fishing industry’s strategy of diversification, known as “fishing down the food web” (Bhathal and Pauly 2008), cannot be sustained in the long-term. More data is needed to be certain, but since overexploitation has dramatically reduced stocks of commercially important fish such as tuna and anchoveta (FAO 2018), it seems highly likely that the new reliance on alternative species will, in turn, denude stocks of these forms of sea-life.</p> <p><em>The last haul of the day is negligible – disappointed and late we turn for shore, heading almost due North on an easterly bearing 73° 27. 015’E. Drop anchor at 5.30 p.m. The impact of the relentlessly throbbing engine on our eardrums only becomes clear when it stops at last. A hollow space is left behind. The crew load a small row-boat and ferry the catch to the market on the beach.</em></p> <p><em>A working day of over 12 hours. The crew does not get weekends.</em></p> <p>And where this chain ends, it seems, must be the collapse of the trawl-fishing industry. Marine-life simply does not have the capacity to reproduce at a rate which will keep pace with the rate of extraction, and so the biodiversity of our oceans will reach such a depleted state that no large-scale fishing will be economically viable. It is true that there are global efforts to reduce the ecological impacts of fishing. However, there is an enormous gulf between allowing marine ecosystems to slowly recover, and bringing them back to a point where they can once again be harvested on a commercial scale.</p> <p>And so, it seems that the sad but inevitable truth is that in many ways, trawler fishing can already be seen to be dead in the water – it is only a matter of time before it sinks completely. Stocks of target-species are already barely commercially viable. The fishmeal industry is no more sustainable in the long term. On the one hand it is difficult to have sympathy for an industry which has literally destroyed its own foundations by overexploiting the resource on which it depends. On the other however, to view the issue from this broad scale misses the finer detail. It misses the impacts on the lives of individual fishers like Anil, Deepak and their crew-mates – Yeshwant the captain and Shrivam the cook, Pintya, Lankesh, Subodh and Keshav; the impacts on the thousand such ‘thalashis’ at Malvan, and the millions more around India’s coastline.</p> <p>The challenge now is finding a brighter future, for both the myriad life-forms that live in our seas, and also the approximately 40 million people that depend on those seas for their livelihoods (FAO 2018). With the demise of the industry these people will find themselves with no means to support themselves and their families. And so it is vital that although the industry will die out—over the next 10, 20 or even 50 years—we do not allow its fishers to fall into the abyss.</p> <p>References</p> <ul> <li> <p>Bhathal, B., and D. Pauly. 2008. “‘Fishing down Marine Food Webs’ and Spatial Expansion of Coastal Fisheries in India, 1950-2000.” Fisheries Research 91 (1): 26–34. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fishres.2007.10.022.</p> </li> <li> <p>Eayrs, S. 2007. “A Guide to Bycatch Reduction in Tropical Shrimp-Trawl Fisheries.” Fao, 124. Edwards, P., and G.L. Allan. 2004. “A Survey of Marine Trash Fish and Fish Meal as Aquaculture Feed Ingredients in Vietnam” 57 (57).</p> </li> <li> <p>FAO. 2018. The State of World Fisheries and Aquaculture 2018 - Meeting the Sustainable Development Goals. THE STATE OF THE WORLD Series of the Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations. Vol. 35. https://doi.org/issn 10.</p> </li> <li> <p>Gillett, R. 2008. “Global Study of Shrimp Fisheries.” Fisheries Bethesda 475: 331 pp.</p> </li> <li> <p>Kelleher, K. 2005. “Discards in the World s Marine Fisheries: An Update.” FAO Fisheries Technical Paper, no. 470: 22. https://doi.org/ISBN 92-5-105289-1.</p> </li> <li> <p>Lobo, A.S., A. Balmford, R. Arthur, and A. Manica. 2010. “Commercializing Bycatch Can Push a Fishery beyond Economic Extinction.” Conservation Letters 3 (4): 277–85. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1755-263X.2010.00117.x.</p> </li> <li> <p>Nunoo, F.K.E., J.O. Boateng, A.M. Ahulu, K.A. Agyekum, and U. Rashid. 2009. “When Trash Fish Is Treasure : The Case of Ghana in West Africa” 96: 167–72. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fishres.2008.10.010.</p> </li> <li> <p>Soykan, C.U., J.E. Moore, R. ??delis, L.B. Crowder, C. Safina, and R.L. Lewison. 2008. “Why Study Bycatch? An Introduction to the Theme Section on Fisheries Bycatch.” Endangered Species Research 5 (2–3): 91–102. https://doi.org/10.3354/esr00175</p> </li> </ul>]]></content><author><name>Mathew Creasey, Ph.D.</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A piece about fisheries at Malvan, co-authored with the brilliant Mathew Creasey, published in Current Conservation 13.4.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Scaly business:A day in the life of a sea snake biologist</title><link href="https://shawn.cheesesnakes.net/blog/2019/DITL/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Scaly business:A day in the life of a sea snake biologist"/><published>2019-07-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-07-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://shawn.cheesesnakes.net/blog/2019/DITL</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://shawn.cheesesnakes.net/blog/2019/DITL/"><![CDATA[<p>What do sea snakes eat? Do different types of sea snakes eat the same things? Do they live in the same places? Do these behaviours change throughout the year? For the past two years I’ve been working in Malvan, Maharashtra, trying to answer these questions. But first there was something I had to figure out: how does one study an animal that spends most of its time underwater? Three words – fishers, boats and nets.</p> <p>Perhaps before I go any further I should explain what a sea snake actually is. They are unique marine reptiles that evolved from land dwelling ancestors in the waters around Australia, around 2 – 3 million years ago. Like all other reptiles they need to breathe air to survive, but can dive for up to 30 minutes at a time in search of food. Some sea snakes may come on to land to rest or to lay eggs - these are known as ‘sea kraits’. True sea snakes on the other hand live their whole lives at sea. To do this, they have evolved to give birth to live young and may have around 20 babies at a time. Sea snakes can be found all the way from Australia in the east to Eastern Coast of Africa. And throughout this range they frequently come into contact with people.</p> <p>Humans have been casting their nets into the oceans in search of food for thousands of years. As the number of people grew, more boats with better nets, lines, hooks and eventually engines began to operate in coastal waters. While we got better at catching large quantities of the tasty seafood we wanted, our nets would often also bring up other, inedible types of sea-life we hadn’t meant to catch and had no use for. This is known as ‘bycatch’ and it affects scores of marine organisms in coastal areas and oceans around the world. Sea snakes are very often caught as bycatch in fishers’ nets at Malvan, and we don’t know very much about what effect this is having on these marine reptiles.</p> <p>To try and find out, every morning my project assistant Yogesh and I try to wake up before the sun rises. The fishers set out well before it gets light, around 2am, and return to shore just after dawn, so that is the best time to meet them and see what they have caught. Taking our notepads and snake hooks (metal hooks with which we can gently pick up the snakes without being bitten), we walk along the beach. The fishers start with a bit of black tea and then put on plastic overalls and start sorting their catch. Yogesh and I wave at our fisher friends and ask them what they caught that night. Every so often, a fisher will call us over. “Maruza!”, he’ll say, which means sea snake in the local Malvani. We then carefully collect the snake from the net and ask fishermen information about where they caught it, what depth the net was at, and what the habitat is like on the sea floor in that area, to help us understand more about where the sea snakes are spending their time. Sometimes, we may show up late for the catch and then get earful from the fishers for sleeping in. On average we get around 3 – 4 snakes each morning.</p> <p>We then take these snakes back to our field base where we measure them and check their stomachs for food, or eggs if it’s a female. We also take blood and scale samples which will tell us about what they’ve been eating and where they’ve been moving over the past few weeks and months. Once we have collected our data, we take the snakes back to the beach and release them back into the water, waving goodbye as they swim away.</p> <p>Through this work, with the help of our fisher friends, we hope to come a few steps closer to understanding how humans and sea snakes interact together in their shared environment and how they can live together peacefully.</p>]]></content><author><name>Shawn Dsouza</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A DITL published in Current Conservation Kids 13.3.]]></summary></entry></feed>